Guide to the Hart Crane Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Hart Crane Papers,
ca.1909-1937
Crane, Hart, 1899-1932.
15 linear ft. (ca. 1,200 items in 25 boxes; 3 reels (motion picture); 1 framed painting).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079683
Biographical Note
American poet.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, and memorabilia of the American poet, Hart Crane, range in date over most of his active life. This collection includes over 500 letters written by Crane to members of his family and close friends and received by him from his family and prominent contemporary authors (Eugene O'Neill, Sherwood Anderson, T. S. Eliot, Alfred Steiglitz, Waldo Frank, Allan Tate, etc.). Among these is a group of letters written to Mrs. Crane upon Crane's death. There is correspondence and documents relating to his books, THE BRIDGE, WHITE BUILDINGS, and THE COLLECTED POEMS. Also present are most of the original manuscripts of Crane's major works ("The Bridge," "White Buildings," "West Indies Poems," etc) with corrections and additions in Crane's hand. Included here are a number of drafts of poems of his earlier period. The is also a copy of the 16mm. motion picture "In Search of Hart Crane."
In addition there is one box of notes by Jethro Robinson relating to his Ph.D. dissertation, as well as a large group of photographs taken by Crane in Mexico with inscriptions and identifications in his hand and a group of Crane's scrapbooks, family photographs and mementoes. Accompanying the collection is a group of books from Hart Crane's library many of which are signed copies and a group of periodical material which relates to Crane.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
Series III: Cataloged letters, manuscripts and documents not on microfilm
Series IV: Correspondence
Series V: Manuscripts
Series VI: Documents
Series VII: Drawings and Paintings
Series VIII: Cataloged manuscripts other than by Hart Crane
Subjects
Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941.; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965.; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953.; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946.; American literature.; American poetry--20th century.; Drafts (literary).; Drawings.; Manuscripts (literary).; Motion pictures.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Paintings.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scrapbooks.; Authors.; Poets, American
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1953 M-1953 Purchase
03/29/94 M-94-03-29 Florian-Parmentier book from Crane's library 2293B-(Rare Book) Purchase
Alternate Formats
Boxes 1-11 are on microfilm.
Gift of the Mildred Andrews Foundation (via Peter Putnam), 1985 (motion picture film).
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  Boxes 1-11 are on microfilm, except for some material noted below
  - A-Crane, Clarence A., to 1915 (Box 1)
  - Crane, Clarence A., 1917-1931 - Crane, Grace Hart, 1915-1925 (Box 2)
  - Crane, Grace Hart, 1926-1947 (Box 3)
  - Crane, Hart, 1910-1924 (Box 4)
  - Crane, Hart, 1925-1932 (Box 5)
  - Crosby, H (Box 6)
  - J-R (Box 7)
  - S-Z (Box 8)
- Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
  - A-M (Box 9)
  - N-Z (Box 10)
  - Cape Hatteras. [n.p.], [n.d.], (t.ms. ) (Box 11)
    [Late draft]
- Series III: Cataloged letters, manuscripts and documents not on microfilm
  - (Box 12)
- Series IV: Correspondence
  - Cowley, Peggy B., 1957-1962
  - Crane, Hart. 11 Nov. 1929, Spring 1931, & 22 May 1931
  - Ridge, Lola. 5 April 1919
  - Robson, Peggy M. To Susan Jenkins Brown, 7 Sept.1956
  - Tate, Allen To Maurice Zolotow, 8 Jan. 1936
  - Tate, Allen To Gerard Previn Meyer, 4 Nov. 1969
- Series V: Manuscripts
  - Crane, Hart Address books, ((2) )
  - Crane, Hart Poems copied by Hart Crane, (4 p. )
  - Crane, Hart "Vocabulary,", (15p. )
- Series VI: Documents
  - Crane, Hart. Printed document, signed, 2 April 1927., (2p. )
  - Arranged clippings, reviews, printed poems and letters, envelopes, etc (Box 12)
- Series VII: Drawings and Paintings
  - Crane, Hart Drawings and painting by Hart Crane (cataloged) (Box 13)
- Series VIII: Cataloged manuscripts other than by Hart Crane
  - Brenner, Anita
  - Brown, Susan Jenkins
  - Cowley, Malcolm
  - Crane, Grace Hart
  - Horton, Philip
  - Jiménez, Juan Ramón
  - Loveman, Samuel
  - Tate, Alan
  - Turner, Maude Sperry
  - Weber, Brom
  - Arranged miscellaneous manuscripts and printed material other than by Hart Crane (Box 14)
  - Photographs, cataloged and arranged, (including photograph album of Mexico) (Box 15)
  - Photographs (framed) (Box 16)
  - Photographs and pictures (framed) (Box 17)
  - Jethro Robinson notes (Box 18)
  - Photographic copies of letters and manuscripts in collections in other libraries. (Box 19)
    [NOT TO BE USED WITHOUT THE PERMISSION OF THE LIBRARIAN FOR RARE BOOKS AND MANUSCRIPTS]
  - Crane, Hart Seven Lyrics by Hart Crane. (Box 20)
  - Literary manuscripts of Hart Crane
  - Literary manuscripts of Hart Crane. Typescripts, carbons, notebooks, (2) (Box 21)
  - National Educational Television Film: "In Search of Hart Crane." Interviews. (Box 22)
  - Crane, Grace Hart Books from the library of Grace Hart Crane (Box 23)
  - Books from the library of Grace Hart Crane (cont.) (Box 24)
  - Cataloged correspondence and documents relating to "The Bridge," "White Buildings," and "Collected Poems." (Box 25)
  - National Educational Television "In Search of Hart Crane.", (Three reels of film)